Twenty years ago,
قبل عشرين عاماً مضت،
when I was a barrister and human rights lawyer
عندما كنت محامي حقوق إنسان
in full-time legal practice in London,
في الممارسة القانونية بدوام كامل في لندن،
and the highest court in the land
وأعلى محكمة في بلد
still convened, some would say by an accident of history,
لا يزال مُنعقداً كما قد يقول البعض بمصادفة التاريخ،
in this building here,
في هذا المبنى حيث نحن الآن،
I met a young man who had just quit his job
التقيت شاباً كان قد ترك عمله للتو
in the British Foreign Office.
في مكتب الخارجية البريطانية.
When I asked him, "Why did you leave,"
عندما سألته: "لماذا تركت عملك؟"
he told me this story.
أخبرني بهذه القصة.
He had gone to his boss one morning and said,
ذهب إلى مديره في العمل ذات صباح وقال له:
"Let's do something about human rights abuses in China."
"فالنفعل شيئاً حيال انتهاكات حقوق الإنسان في الصين."
And his boss had replied,
فأجاب مديره:
"We can't do anything about human rights abuses in China
"لا نستطيع فعل أي شيئ حيال انتهاكات حقوق الإنسان في الصين
because we have trade relations with China."
لأن لنا علاقات تجارية مع الصين."
So my friend went away with his tail between his legs,
فعاد صديقي أدراجه خائباً،
and six months later, he returned again to his boss,
بعدها بستة أشهر، عاد مجدداً إلى مديره،
and he said this time,
فقال له هذه المرة:
"Let's do something about human rights in Burma,"
فالنفعل شيئاً حيال حقوق الإنسان في بورما،"
as it was then called.
كما قال قبل ذلك.
His boss once again paused
فصمت مديره ثانيةً
and said, "Oh, but we can't do anything about human rights in Burma
ثم قال: "أوه، لكن لا نستطيع فعل شيئ حيال حقوق الإنسان في بورما
because we don't have any trade relations with Burma."
لأنه ليس لنا علاقات تجارية مع بورما."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This was the moment he knew he had to leave.
حينها عرف أن عليه أن يغادر.
It wasn't just the hypocrisy that got to him.
لم يكن الأمر متعلقاً بالنفاق فحسب.
It was the unwillingness of his government
بل كان عدم رغبة حكومته
to engage in conflict with other governments,
في الإنخراط في صراع مع حكومات أخرى،
in tense discussions,
في مناقشات متوترة،
all the while, innocent people were being harmed.
طول الوقت، كان الأبرياء يتعرضون للأذى.
We are constantly told
يتم إخبارنا باستمرار
that conflict is bad
أن الصراع شيئ سيئ
that compromise is good;
وأن المساومة شيئ جيد؛
but consensus is good;
ولكن التراضي شيئ جيد؛
that conflict is bad
أن الصراع شيئ سيئ
and collaboration is good.
وأن التعاون شيئ جيد.
But in my view,
ولكن من وجهة نظري،
that's far too simple a vision of the world.
رؤية العالم هذه بالغة البساطة.
We cannot know
لا نستطيع أن نعرف
whether conflict is bad
ما إذا كان الصراع شيئاً سيئاً
unless we know who is fighting,
ما لم نعرف من يتقاتل.
why they are fighting
ولماذا يتقاتلون
and how they are fighting.
وكيف يقاتلون.
And compromises can be thoroughly rotten
ويمكن أن تكون التنازلات فاسدةً تماماً
if they harm people who are not at the table,
إن تسببت بالأذى لأناس لا علاقة لهم بالأمر،
people who are vulnerable, disempowered,
من هم عرضة للخطر وغير قادرين،
people whom we have an obligation to protect.
من علينا الالتزام بحمايتهم.
Now, you might be somewhat skeptical of a lawyer
الآن، قد تكونون متشككين نوعاً ما في محامي
arguing about the benefits of conflict
يجادل في فوائد الصراع
and creating problems for compromise,
وخلق مشاكل للتسوية
but I did also qualify as a mediator,
ولكن تم تأهيلي أيضاً كوسيط،
and these days, I spend my time giving talks about ethics for free.
وهذه الأيام، أقضي وقتي أقدّم خطابات عن الأخلاق مجاناً.
So as my bank manager likes to remind me, I'm downwardly mobile.
فكما يحب مديري في البنك أن يذكّرني، فأنا متحرك إلى الأسفل.
But if you accept my argument,
لكن إذا ما قبلت حجتي،
it should change not just the way we lead our personal lives,
فسوف تغير حتماً ليس فقط الطريقة التي نقود بها حياتنا الخاصة،
which I wish to put to one side for the moment,
والتي أتمنى أن لا أتحدث عنها حالياً،
but it will change the way we think about major problems
ولكنها سوف تغير الطريقة التي نفكر بها في المشاكل العظيمة
of public health and the environment.
بخصوص الصحة العامة والبيئة.
Let me explain.
دعوني أوضح ذلك.
Every middle schooler in the United States,
كل طالب في المرحلة الوسطى في الولايات المتحدة،
my 12-year-old daughter included,
بما فيهم ابنتي ذات ال12 عام،
learns that there are three branches of government,
يتعلمون أنه يوجد ثلاثة أفرع للحكومة،
the legislative, the executive and the judicial branch.
الفرع التشريعي والتنفيذي والقضائي.
James Madison wrote,
كتب جايمس ماديسون،
"If there is any principle more sacred in our Constitution,
"إن كان هناك من مبدأ أكثر قدسية في دستورنا،
and indeed in any free constitution,
بل في أي دستور حر،
than any other,
دون غيره،
it is that which separates
فهو ذلك الذي يفصل
the legislative, the executive and the judicial powers."
السلطات التشريعية والتنفيذية والقضائية عن بعضها البعض."
Now, the framers were not just concerned
الآن، لم يكن واضعو الإطار معنيون فحسب
about the concentration and exercise of power.
بتركيز وممارسة السلطة.
They also understood the perils of influence.
فهموا أيضاً مخاطر التأثير.
Judges cannot determine the constitutionality of laws
لا يستطيع القضاة تحديد دستورية القوانين
if they participate in making those laws,
إن شاركوا في وضع هذه القوانين،
nor can they hold the other branches of government accountable
كذلك لا يستطيعون مساءلة أفرع الحكومة الآخرى
if they collaborate with them
إذا ما تعاونوا معهم
or enter into close relationships with them.
أو توغلوا في علاقات متينة معهم.
The Constitution is, as one famous scholar put it,
القانون كما قال أحد العلماء المشهورين،
"an invitation to struggle."
"دعوة للصراع."
And we the people are served
ونحن الشعب نستفيد
when those branches do, indeed, struggle with each other.
عندما تتصارع هذه الفروع حقاً مع بعضها البعض.
Now, we recognize the importance of struggle
الآن، نعرف أهمية الصراع
not just in the public sector
ليس فقط في القطاع العام
between our branches of government.
فيما بين أفرع الحكومية.
We also know it too in the private sector,
نعرف ذلك أيضاً في القطاع الخاص،
in relationships among corporations.
في العلاقات بين الشركات.
Let's imagine that two American airlines get together and agree
فالنتخيل أن شركتي الطيران الأمريكيتين إتفقتا
that they will not drop the price
على عدم خفض سعر
of their economy class airfares below 250 dollars a ticket.
تذاكر الدرجة الاقتصادية أقل من 250 دولارً للتذكرة الواحدة.
That is collaboration, some would say collusion,
يمثل ذلك تعاوناً وقد يسميه البعض تواطؤاً،
not competition,
وليس منافسة،
and we the people are harmed
ونحن الشعب المتضرر من ذلك
because we pay more for our tickets.
لأننا ندفع المزيد من أجل تذاكرنا.
Imagine similarly two airlines were to say,
على نفس المنوال، تخيّل شركتي طيران قالتا:
"Look, Airline A, we'll take the route from LA to Chicago,"
"انظر، ستسلك شركة الطيران أ الطريق من لوس أنجلوس حتى شيكاغو،"
and Airline B says, "We'll take the route from Chicago to DC,
وشركة الطيران ب قالت: "سنسلك الطريق من شيكاغو وحتى واشنطن العاصمة،
and we won't compete."
وسوف لن ندخل في منافسة."
Once again, that's collaboration or collusion instead of competition,
مرة أخرى، يعتبر ذلك تعاوناً أو تواطؤاً وليس منافسة،
and we the people are harmed.
ونحن الشعب المتضررون من ذلك.
So we understand the importance of struggle
لذلك نفهم أهمية الصراع
when it comes to relationships between branches of government,
حينما يتعلق الأمر بالعلاقات بين أفرع الحكومة،
the public sector.
في القطاع العام.
We also understand the importance of conflict
ندرك كذلك أهمية الصراع
when it comes to relationships among corporations,
حينما يتعلق الأمر بالعلاقات بين الشركات،
the private sector.
في القطاع الخاص.
But where we have forgotten it
ولكن ما نسيناه
is in the relationships between the public and the private.
هو في العلاقات بين العام والخاص.
And governments all over the world are collaborating with industry
كل الحكومات حول العالم تتعاون مع الصناعة
to solve problems of public health and the environment,
لحل مشاكل الصحة العامة والبيئة،
often collaborating with the very corporations
وغالباً ما تتعاون مع الشركات ذاتها
that are creating or exacerbating the problems they are trying to solve.
التي تخلق أو تفاقم المشاكل التي يحاولون حلها.
We are told that these relationships
تم إخبارنا أن هذه العلاقات
are a win-win.
هي علاقات مصلحة متبادلة.
But what if someone is losing out?
ولكن ماذا لو خسر أحد ما؟
Let me give you some examples.
اسمحوا لي أن أعطيكم بعض الأمثلة.
A United Nations agency decided to address a serious problem:
قررت وكالة الأمم المتحدة حلّ مشكلة عويصة:
poor sanitation in schools in rural India.
سوء النظام الصحي في المدارس في المناطق الريفية في الهند.
They did so not just in collaboration with national and local governments
فعلوا ذلك ليس فقط بالتعاون مع الحكومات الوطنية والمحلية
but also with a television company
ولكن أيضاً مع شركة تلفزيونية
and with a major multinational soda company.
وكذلك مع شركة صودا كبرى متعددة الجنسيات.
In exchange for less than one million dollars,
مقابل أقل من مليون دولار،
that corporation received the benefits of a months-long promotional campaign
استلمت تلك الشركة فوائد شهور من الدعاية الترويجية
including a 12-hour telethon
بالإضافة لبرنامج خيري امتد ل 12 ساعة
all using the company's logo and color scheme.
كل ذلك باستخدام شعار الشركة ولون المشروع.
This was an arrangement
كان هذا اتفاقاً
which was totally understandable
والذي كان مفهوماً تماماً
from the corporation's point of view.
من وجهة نظر الشركة.
It enhances the reputation of the company
عزز ذلك من سمعة الشركة
and it creates brand loyalty for its products.
كما خلق ذلك ولاءً للعلامة التجارية لمنتجاتها.
But in my view,
ولكن من وجهة نظري،
this is profoundly problematic for the intergovernmental agency,
يعتبر هذا أمراً إشكالياً للغاية للوكالة الحكومية الدولية،
an agency that has a mission to promote sustainable living.
وهي وكالة لديها مهمة لتعزيز المعيشة المستدامة.
By increasing consumption of sugar-sweetened beverages
عن طريق زيادة استهلاك المشروبات المحلاة بالسكر
made from scarce local water supplies and drunk out of plastic bottles
مصنوعة من إمدادات مياه محلية شحيحة وتشرب من قوارير بلاستيكية
in a country that is already grappling with obesity,
في بلد يصارع السمنة سلفاً،
this is neither sustainable from a public health
ليس هذا مستداماً من وجهة نظر صحة عامة
nor an environmental point of view.
ولا وجهة نظر بيئية.
And in order to solve one public health problem,
ومن أجل حل مشكلة واحدة متعلقة بالصحة العامة،
the agency is sowing the seeds
تزرع الوكالة بذور
of another.
مشكلة أخرى.
This is just one example of dozens I discovered
هذا مثال واحد فحسب من بين العشرات التي اكتشفتها
in researching a book on the relationships between government and industry.
خلال بحثي لكتاب عن العلاقات بين الحكومة والصناعة.
I could also have told you about the initiatives in parks
ربما أخبرتكم أيضاً عن المبادرات في الحدائق
in London and throughout Britain,
في لندن وعبر بريطانيا،
involving the same company, promoting exercise,
تتضمن نفس ممارسات الشركة الترويجية،
or indeed of the British government creating voluntary pledges
أو في الحقيقة حول الحكومة البريطانية وهي تخلق تعهدات تطوعية
in partnership with industry
بالشراكة مع الصناعة
instead of regulating industry.
بدلاً من تنظيم الصناعة.
These collaborations or partnerships have become the paradigm in public health,
أصبحت هذه التعاونات أو الشراكات نموذجاً في الصحة العامة،
and once again, they make sense from the point of view of industry.
ومجدداً، تكون منطقية من وجهة نظر الصناعة.
It allows them to frame public health problems and their solutions
يسمح لهم ذلك بتأطير مشاكل الصحة العامة وحلولها
in ways that are least threatening to,
بطرق أقل تهديداً،
most consonant with their commercial interests.
ومنسجمة أكثر مع مصالحهم التجارية.
So obesity becomes a problem
لذلك أصبحت السمنة مشكلة
of individual decision-making,
اتخاذ قرار فردي
of personal behavior,
لسلوك شخصي،
personal responsibility and lack of physical activity.
مسؤولية شخصية ونقص في النشاط البدني.
It is not a problem,
ليست هي مشكلة،
when framed this way,
عند تأطيرها بهذه الطريقة،
of a multinational food system involving major corporations.
من نظام أطعمة متعدد الجنسيات يشمل شركات كبرى.
And again, I don't blame industry.
ومرة أخرى، أنا لا ألوم الصناعة.
Industry naturally engages in strategies of influence
من الطبيعي أن تنخرط الشركات في خطط تأثير
to promote its commercial interests.
من أجل ترويج مصالحها التجارية.
But governments have a responsibility
لكن الحكومة على عاتقها مسؤولية
to develop counterstrategies
لتطوير خطط مضادة
to protect us
لحمايتنا
and the common good.
والصالح العام.
The mistake that governments are making
الخطأ الذي تقع فيه الحكومات
when they collaborate in this way
حينما تتعاون بهذه الطريقة
with industry
مع الصناعة
is that they conflate
هي أنها تخلط
the common good
الصالح العام
with common ground.
مع الأرضية المشتركة.
When you collaborate with industry,
عندما تتعاون مع الصناعة،
you necessarily put off the table
فأنت تطعن لا محالة
things that might promote the common good to which industry will not agree.
في أشياء ربما تعزز الصالح العام والتي ستكون ضد مصالح الصناعة.
Industry will not agree to increased regulation
لن توافق الصناعة على زيادة التنظيم
unless it believes this will stave off even more regulation
ما لم تؤمن أن ذلك سيمنع مزيداً من التنظيم
or perhaps knock some competitors out of the market.
أو ربما قد يرمي ببعض المنافسين خارج السوق.
Nor can companies agree to do certain things,
لن توافق الشركات على فعل أشياء محددة،
for example raise the prices of their unhealthy products,
على سبيل المثال رفع أسعار منتجاتهم غير الصحية،
because that would violate competition law,
لأن ذلك قد ينتهك قانون المنافسة،
as we've established.
كا تأكدنا من ذلك.
So our governments should not confound
لذلك يجب على حكوماتنا عدم الخلط
the common good and common ground,
بين الصالح العام والأرضية المشتركة،
especially when common ground means reaching agreement with industry.
خصوصاً عندما تعني الأرضية المشتركة الوصول لاتفاق مع الصناعة.
I want to give you another example,
أريد إعطاءكم مثالاً آخر،
moving from high-profile collaboration
لننتقل من التعاون رفيع المستوى
to something that is below ground
لشيئ أقل
both literally and figuratively:
سواء حرفياً أو مجازياً:
the hydraulic fracturing of natural gas.
التكسير الهيدروليكي للغاز الطبيعي.
Imagine that you purchase a plot of land
تخيل أنك اشتريت قطعة أرض
not knowing the mineral rights have been sold.
ولا تعرف أن الحقوق المعدنية قد تم بيعها.
This is before the fracking boom.
هذا قبل طفرة التكسير.
You build your dream home on that plot,
بنيت بيت أحلامك على تلك الأرض،
and shortly afterwards,
وبعدها بفترة قصيرة،
you discover that a gas company is building a well pad on your land.
تكتشف أن شركة غاز تحفر بئراً على أرضك.
That was the plight of the Hallowich family.
كانت تلك مكيدة عائلة هالويتش.
Within a very short period of time,
خلال فترة قصيرة من الزمن،
they began to complain of headaches,
بدأوا في الشكوى من الصداع،
of sore throats, of itchy eyes,
ومن أوجاع الحلق وحساسية العيون،
in addition to the interference of the noise, vibration
بالإضافة لتداخل الضوضاء والإهتزازات
and the bright lights from the flaring of natural gas.
والأضواء الساطعة من حرق الغاز الطبيعي.
They were very vocal in their criticisms,
كانوا صاخبين جدا في انتقاداتهم،
and then they fell silent.
ثم صمتوا بعدها.
And thanks to the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, where this image appeared,
وبفضل بيتسبرغ بوست-جازيت، حيث ظهرت هذه الصورة،
and one other newspaper, we discovered why they fell silent.
وصحيفة أخرى، اكتشفنا لماذا صمتوا.
The newspapers went to the court and said, "What happened to the Hallowiches?"
ذهبت الصحف إلى المحكمة وقالت: "ماذا حدث لعائلة هالويتش؟"
And it turned out the Hallowiches had made a secret settlement
ثم اتضح بعدها أن عائلة هالويتش ابرمت اتفاقاً سرياً
with the gas operators, and it was a take-it-or-leave-it settlement.
مع مشغّلي الغاز، وقد كان اتفاقاً ملزماً.
The gas company said,
قالت شركة الغاز:
you can have a six-figure sum
ستحصلون على مبلغ من ستة أرقام
to move elsewhere and start your lives again,
لترحلوا إلى مكان آخر وتبدأوا حياة جديدة،
but in return
ولكن بالمقابل
you must promise not to speak of your experience with our company,
يجب أن تعدوا بعدم التحدث عن تجربتكم مع شركتنا،
not to speak of your experience with fracking,
لا تتحدثوا عن تجربتكم مع التكسير،
not to speak about the health consequences
لا تتحدثوا عن الأضرار الصحية
that might have been revealed by a medical examination.
التي قد يسرّبها الفحص الطبي.
Now, I do not blame the Hallowiches for accepting
الآن، أنا لا ألوم عائلة هالويتش لموافقتهم
a take-it-or-leave-it settlement
على اتفاق ملزم
and starting their lives elsewhere.
وبدء حياتهم في مكان آخر.
And one can understand
ويستطيع الواحد منا أن يفهم
why the company would wish to silence a squeaky wheel.
لماذا قد ترغب الشركة في إسكات عجلة صارخة.
What I want to point the finger at is the legal and regulatory system,
ما أريد أن أشير له هو النظام القانوني والتنظيمي،
a system in which there are networks of agreements
وهو نظام يحوي شبكات اتفاقيات
just like this one
مثل هذه بالضبط
which serve to silence people and seal off data points
التي تعمل على إسكات الناس وختم نقاط البيانات
from public health experts and epidemiologists,
من خبراء صحة عامة وعلماء أوبئة،
a system in which regulators
نظام يقوم فيه المنظمون
will even refrain from issuing a violation notice
بالامتناع حتى من إصدار مذكرة انتهاك
in the event of pollution
في حال حدوث تلوث
if the landowner and the gas company
إذا ما توصل صاحب الأرض وشركة الغاز
agree to settle.
على تسوية.
This is a system which isn't just bad from a public health point of view;
هذا نظام ليس سيئاً فحسب من وجهة نظر الصحة العامة؛
it exposes hazards to local families
بل يعرّض العائلات المحلية للخطر
who remain in the dark.
تلك التي تبقى في الظلام.
Now, I have given you two examples not because they are isolated examples.
الآن، أعطيتكم مثالين ليس لأنهما مثالان معزولان.
They are examples of a systemic problem.
بل هي أمثلة لمشكلة ممنهجة.
I could share some counterexamples,
يمكنني أن أشارككم بعض الأمثلة المضادة،
the case for example of the public official
مثل حالة المسؤول العام
who sues the pharmaceutical company
الذي استخدم شركة صيدلانية
for concealing the fact
لإخفاء الحقيقة
that its antidepressant increases suicidal thoughts in adolescents.
أن مضادات الإكتئاب التي تبيعها تزيد من أفكار الإنتحار لدى المراهقين.
I can tell you about the regulator who went after the food company
يمكنني إخباركم عن المنظّم الذي اقتفى أثر شركة غذائية
for exaggerating the purported health benefits of its yogurt.
لمبالغتها في الفوائد الصحية المزعومة للزبادي الذي تبيعه.
And I can tell you about the legislator
كما يمكنني أن أخبركم عن المشرّع
who despite heavy lobbying directed at both sides of the aisle
الذي وعلى الرغم من الضغط الشديد الموجه من كلا الجانبين
pushes for environmental protections.
دفع بالحماية البيئية.
These are isolated examples,
هذه أمثلة معزولة،
but they are beacons of light in the darkness,
لكنها منارات ضوء تنير العتمة،
and they can show us the way.
كما أنها تهدينا الطريق.
I began by suggesting that sometimes we need to engage in conflict.
بدأت باقتراح أننا أحياناً نحتاج إلى الإنخراط في الصراع.
Governments should tussle with,
ينبغي على الحكومات أن تصارع،
struggle with, at times engage in direct conflict with corporations.
عليها أن تنخرط في صراع مباشر مع الشركات.
This is not because governments are inherently good
ليس هذا بسبب أن الحكومات في طبيعتها جيدة
and corporations are inherently evil.
وأن الشركات سيئة.
Each is capable of good or ill.
كلاهما يحمل الجيد والسيئ.
But corporations understandably act to promote their commercial interests,
لكن من المفهوم أن الشركات تعمل لتعزيز مصالحها التجارية،
and they do so either sometimes undermining or promoting the common good.
وهم يفعلون ذلك أحياناً إما لتقويض أو تعزيز الصالح العام.
But it is the responsibility of governments
ولكنها مسؤولية الحكومات
to protect and promote the common good.
في حماية وتعزيز الصالح العام.
And we should insist
وعلينا أن نصرّ
that they fight to do so.
أنهم يحاربون للقيام بذلك.
This is because governments
هذا بسبب أن الحكومات
are the guardians
هم حماة
of public health;
الصحة العامة؛
governments are the guardians
الحكومات هم حماة
of the environment;
البيئة؛
and it is governments
كذلك الحكومات
that are guardians
هم حماة
of these essential parts of our common good.
هذه الأجزاء الأساسية من صالحنا العام.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)